Guide to the Progressive Librarians Council Correspondence TAM 064
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Progressive Librarians Council Correspondence
Bulk, 1939-1944
1930-1944, (Bulk 1939-1944)
TAM 064
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.5 Linear feet (1 box)
The Progressive Librarians Council (1939-1944) was a Communist-led professional association. The collection contains correspondence and a few other items.
Progressive Librarians Council
Provenance
Transferred from the Rand School Library, 1962.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Progressive Librarians Council (1939-1944) was a professional association that followed the political leadership of the Communist Party.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondence, much of it routine, is almost entirely with librarians (PLC members and others), and relates to the publication of the P.L.C. Bulletin, and to the promotion of open, efficient libraries, as well as progressive legislation, civil rights and links with organized labor. A few letters contain discussion of issues relating to the American Library Association. Principal correspondents are Theodore E. Norton (chairman), Edwin Castagna (vice-chairman) and Bertha Schulman (secretary-treasurer). There is also correspondence with Homero Seris and Juan Viceris, two Spanish librarians living in exile in Mexico, who received financial assistance from the PLC. The collection also contains constitutions, speeches and statements by Norton, and a few items relating to the British Columbia Library Association.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
The files are grouped into1 series:
Inventory
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
American Library Association.; British Columbia Library Association.; Castagna, Edwin, 1909-; Norton, Theodore E.; P.L.C. bulletin.; Schuman, Bertha.; Seris, Homero, 1879-1969.; Viceris, Juan.; Correspondence.; Libraries and communism--United States.; Libraries--Spain.; Library science--United States--Societies, etc.; Progressivism (United States politics); Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939--Refugees--Mexico.
- Inventory
  - British Columbia Library Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitutions, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Pre-History & Founding), 1930, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Aid to Spanish Refugee Librarians Homero Seris & Juan Viceris), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1942-Jun 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1942-Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Norton, Theodore E.: Speeches & Statements, ca.1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)